Student League for Industrial Democracy Records TAM.024
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Student League for Industrial Democracy Records
1934-1936; 1946-1966
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Student League for Industrial Democracy (U.S.)
Vickers, George
TAM.024
5.5 Linear Feet in eleven manuscript boxes.
Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) was a radical student group descended from the Student League for Industrial Democracy (SLID), the student branch of the League for Industrial Democracy (LID), a social democratic organization. SDS was expelled from the LID in 1965 and gained national prominence in the late 1960s as SDS. The records contain predominantly SLID material including conference and convention proceedings, correspondence, minutes of national executive committee meetings, membership files, and reports of committees, student secretaries, chapters and other activities.
Box 1-11
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged chronologically.
Historical/Biographical Note
Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) is a radical student group that descended from the Intercollegiate Socialist Society (ISS) which was founded in 1905. The ISS changed its name in 1921 to the League for Industrial Democracy (LID), a social-democratic educational and organizational group. Its student branch, the Student League for Industrial Democracy (SLID), merged with National Student League in 1935 to form American Student Union (ASU) but soon split over ASUs alleged communist affiliations. SLID revived in 1946 changing its name to Students for a Democratic Society in 1959. It was expelled from the LID in 1965 and gained national prominence in the late 1960s as SDS.
Scope and Contents note
The records contain predominantly SLID material including conference and convention proceedings, minutes of national executive committee meetings, membership files, and reports of committees, student secretaries, chapters and other activities. Includes correspondence of student field secretary James Farmer (1952-1955), and student secretary Gabriel Kolko. Other correspondence relates to Young People's Socialist League, Co-operative Commonwealth Youth Movement (Canada), International Union of Socialist Youth, National Student Association, and Students for Democratic Action. Also some unpublished pamphlet material. SDS material (1962-1966) includes internal documents, correspondence among Tom Hayden, Rennie Davis, Paul Booth, Todd Gitlin, and Lee Webb, and reports on projects such as ERAP (Economic Research and Action Project) and PREP (Peace Research and Education Project).
Separated Materials
Three boxes of printed material were removed from the collection and consolidated with the Students for Democratic Society Printed Ephemera Collection (PE 035).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Provenance is unknown for boxes 1-10, however we believe that the League of Industrial Democracy gifted the Student League for Industrial Democracy Records in 1964. The accession number associated with this gift is 1967.001.
George Vickers sent a gift of internal documents of the Students for a Democratic Society, correspondence in the early period between the leaders Tom Hayden, Todd Gitlin, Paul Booth, Lee Webb, Rennie Davis, and reports from local projects such as ERAP and PREP in September 1972, which is found in Box 11. The accession number associated with this gift is 1964.002.
Correspondence.; Minutes (administrative records); Socialism and youth -- United States.; Proceedings.; Student movements -- United States.; Student League for Industrial Democracy (U.S.); Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.).; Vickers, George
- Unity with National Student League, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Convention, 1934, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- National Executive Committee Minutes, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Strike against War, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Constitution, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous and Play, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Chapter Charters, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- December Organizing Conference, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- League for Industrial Democracy Student Committee, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- National Executive Committee Minutes, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Speakers, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Student Secretary Report, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Constitution-Chapter-National, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- April Convention, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Speakers, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Financial Report, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- League for Industrial Democracy Student Committee, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- National Executive Committee, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- December Convention, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Student Secretary's Report Personnel, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- World Student Congress, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Correspondence, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- League for Industrial Democracy Student Committee, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- National Convention, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- National and Chapter, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- National Executive Committee, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Research Health Care and Housing, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Speakers, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Student Secretary's Report, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- New Leader, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Radio Broadcasts, 1946-1949 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- United Christian Youth Movement, 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Young People's Socialist League-Socialist Party correspondence, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- National and Chapter, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- National Executive Committee, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Student Opinion Survey, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Student Secretary's Report, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Training Program UAW, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Boston Conference, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Convention, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- National and Chapter, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- National Executive Committee, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Outlook, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Student Secretary's Report, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Convention, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- League for Industrial Democracy Student Committee, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- National and Chapter, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- National Executive Committee, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Student Secretary's Report, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- FDR-CIO Camp, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- LID Student Committee, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- National and Chapter, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- National Executive Committee, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Student Dues Receipts, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Student Secretary's Report, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- World, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Cornfeld, Bernard. "Leadership Training in an Oriented Agency – Camp Three Arrows" (M.A. Thesis), 1954 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_f915262a4f5fa9f0ba3889232209bed3)
- Camp Three Arrows, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Charters, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Convention, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Field Secretary's Report, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Harold Lewack's Organizing Reports, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- National Executive Committee, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Spring Conference, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Student Questionnaires, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Young People's Socialist League Correspondence, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Camp Three Arrows, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Conference, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Convention, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- FDR-CIO Camps, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Field Secretary's Report, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- National Executive Committee, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Camp Three Arrows, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- ILGWU Training Institute, 1955-1958 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Internat'l Confederation of Free Trade Unions, 1955-1956 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- National and Chapter, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- National Executive Committee, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Bertell Ollman, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Financial Reports, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Hungary – Appeal and Statements, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Monitor-Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Camp Three Arrows, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Convention, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- LID Student Committee, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- NAC, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- National and Chapter, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Monitor – Unpublished Material, 1957-1958 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Camp Three Arrows, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Convention, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Moscow Youth Festival, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- National and Chapter, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Camp Three Arrows, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Convention, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Cornell Conference, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Kolko Correspondence, 1954-1957 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Madison Institute, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Midwestern Field Trip-Susan Guarmati, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- National and Reports, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Student League for Industrial Democracy-Cooperative Commonwealth Federation Youth Study Weekend, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Study Tours, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- NYC Summer Forums, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Publication Lists, 1950's (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Worker priests – Marie T. Dubalem, 1954 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Steward Training – Mildred Bersh, 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Student League for Industrial Democracy research tracts, 1955-1956 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- The Case for Federal Scholarships – D. Cohen, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Camp Three Arrows, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Convention, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Name Change, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- National Executive Committee, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Convention, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Request for information on health insurance for debate, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Civil Rights Study Group, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Congress of Racial Equality, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 16)
- National and Chapter, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Reports: Al Haber, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Summer Conference Misc., 1961 (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Chapters and Charters Applications, undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
- Educational Program - outlines, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
- Field Trips, undated (Box 7, Folder 24)
- Information on Student League for Industrial Democracy employment-agreements, undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
- Lists of Youth Organizations, undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
- McComb, Miss. Hayden Report, undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
- Membership Files, undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
- Members – Past and Present, undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
- Speakers Bureau List, undated (Box 7, Folder 30)
- Statements, undated (Box 8, Folder 31)
- Cooperative Commonwealth Youth Movement-Cooperative Commonwealth University Federation correspondence, 1946-1955 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Cooperative Commonwealth Youth Movement-Cooperative Commonwealth University Federation correspondence, 1956-1958 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- International Development Placement Association, 1952-1953 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- International Union of Socialist Youth: correspondence, 1948-1954 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- International Union of Socialist Youth: correspondence, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- International Union of Socialist Youth: correspondence, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- International Union of Socialist Youth: correspondence, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- International Union of Socialist Youth: Foreign visitors, delegations, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- International Union of Socialist Youth: Formation of North American Bureau of International Union of Socialist Youth, 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- North American Bureau-International Union of Socialist Youth Winter Schools, 1953-1957 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- National Student Association correspondence, 1950s (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Students for Democratic Action correspondence, 1950s (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Student League for Industrial Democracy-Students for Democratic Action correspondence and agreement, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Student Co-ops: North American Student Cooperative League, 1946, 1957 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- James Farmer Correspondence, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- James Farmer Correspondence, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- James Farmer Correspondence, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- James Farmer Correspondence, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Brooklyn, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
- City College of New York, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Colorado, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Columbia, 1956-1958 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Cornell, 1957-1958 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Harvard, 1955-1957 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- London School of Economics, 1956-1957 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- New York Region, 1948-1952 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- New York University, 1954-1958 (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Oberlin College, 1955-1958 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Princeton, 1956-1958 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Temple University, 1956-1957 (Box 10, Folder 12)
- University of Chicago, 1955-1958 (Box 10, Folder 13)
- University of Michigan, 1956-1959 (Box 10, Folder 14)
- University of Wisconsin, 1957-1959 (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Wayne State, 1948, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 16)
- Yale: Correspondence, 1951-1955 (Box 10, Folder 17)
- Yale: Correspondence, 1955-1960 (Box 10, Folder 18)
- Yale: Charter and Activities, 1954-1960 (Box 10, Folder 19)
- Yale: Challenge, 1959, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 20)
- Yale: News Clippings, 1954-1958 (Box 11, Folder 21)
- Students for a Democratic Society Development, 1962-1963 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Students for a Democratic Society National Council and Convention, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Students for a Democratic Society Development, 1963-1964 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Students for a Democratic Society National Council and Development, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Students for a Democratic Society Development, 1964-1965 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Students for a Democratic Society – Economic Research Action Projects, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Students for a Democratic Society Finances, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Students for a Democratic Society – Post, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Students for a Democratic Society National Council and Convention, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Students for a Democratic Society Development, 1965-1966 (Box 11, Folder 10)